Guide to the A.B. Guthrie Jr. Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, Series II
  - Books
    - The Big It (1960)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 24, Folder 322)
    - "The Blue Hen's Chick" (1965)
      "The Blue Hen's Chick" is Guthrie's unpublished autobiography. Few of the manuscripts are dated, and Guthrie's original order has been preserved, even though some chapters appear to be out of numerical sequence. It seems likely that these groupings represent various stages of revision. The section titles in quotation marks are taken from notes by Guthrie.
      - Manuscript, "Original of Blue Hen's Chick."
        - "First introduction to Blue Hen's Chick," typescript original, undated (Box 25, Folder 323)
        - "Chapter Ten," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Thirty," "Return, dear, to Twin Lakes, Bud," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Prologue," typescript original with annotation, undated
        - "Prologue revision," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter One," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 25, Folder 324)
        - "Chapter Three," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Four," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Ten," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 25, Folder 325)
        - "Chapter Eleven," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twelve," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Fourteen," "no dupe, save one," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Fifteen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Sixteen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eighteen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nineteen," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 25, Folder 326)
        - "Chapter Twenty," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty One," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Two," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Three," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Four," "no dupe, save one," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Five," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 25, Folder 327)
        - "Chapter Twenty Six," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Seven," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Eight," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Eight," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Nine," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Thirty," "no dupes, save one," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - Manuscript, "Blue Hen's Chick, Full Duplicate."
        - "Prologue," typescript original and carbon, undated (Box 25, Folder 328)
        - "Chapter One," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Four," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Eleven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twelve," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Fourteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Fifteen," typescript carbon, undated (Box 25, Folder 329)
        - "Chapter Sixteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Eighteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nineteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty One," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Two," typescript carbon, undated (Box 25, Folder 330)
        - "Chapter Twenty Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Four," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Five," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Six," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Seven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Nine," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Thirty," typescript carbon, undated
      - Manuscript, "Bits, Pieces, Discards and Junk, plus editor's notes on first submission."
        - "Chapter III, p. 47 I don't think it knits as well as the...," typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 25, Folder 331)
        - [Chapter One], typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript carbon, undated
        - "September 12, 60, Chapter Three, pages 57-59 (in chapter three carbon copy from Miss Mary Moore Molony)," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Four," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript carbon, undated (Box 25, Folder 332)
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - [Editorial suggestions], typescript original with annotations, undated
        - [Editorial suggestions], typescript original, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," [includes non- sequential pages and writing fragments] typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - Non-sequential pages and writing fragments, typescript carbon, undated (Box 26, Folder 333-336)
      - Manuscript [unidentified version A]
        - "Chapter ?" typescript original with annotation, undated (Box 26, Folder 337)
        - "Chapter Four," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Why, if my gaze..." typescript original, undated
        - "Chapter Eighteen," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter ????" typescript original, undated
        - "Epilogue," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 26, Folder 338)
        - "There was a girl once..." typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter II," handwritten editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter I," handwritten editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter 4," typescript original editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript editorial changes, original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript original editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter Twelve," typescript original editorial changes, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Nine," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Two legal records, one phony,..." typescript photocopy, undated
        - "One day a beggar appeared..." typescript original with annotations, undated
      - Manuscript [unidentified version B]
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 26, Folder 339)
        - "Chapter Four," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "New Chapter 19," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Mary Lizzie had a rich..." typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "My coworkers weren't rude..." typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "We returned with him..." typescript carbon, undated (Box 26, Folder 340)
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "My earliest is..." [chapter one] typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "The joy of hunting..." typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript thermofax with annotations, undated
        - "R.A. Taft, Mercer Island, Washington, J.S.," typescript thermofax with annotations, undated
        - "George Jackson of Choteau..." typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Number to Come, 18 [in pencil]," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter." typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 26, Folder 341)
        - "Chapter 17," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Sixteen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 15," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 14," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 12, changed to chapter 12," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 13, number to come," typescript photocopy with annotations, undated
        - Editor's note to Bud, typescript original and carbons, undated (Box 26, Folder 342)
        - "Chapter 6/5, Bud see page 3," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 10," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Four," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 19/20," typescript original, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter 11/15," typescript original with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," typescript carbon, undated
        - "White space break," typescript original with annotations, undated
      - Manuscript, "extra dupes."
        - "Chapter Ten," typescript carbon, undated (Box 26, Folder 343)
        - "Chapter Eleven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twelve," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Fifteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Sixteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Eighteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nineteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty," typescript carbon, undated (Box 26, Folder 344)
        - "Chapter Twenty One," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Two," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Three," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Five," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Six," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Seven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Twenty Eight," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Prologue, Blue Hen's Chick 2/3/64," typescript photocopy, 1964 Feb 3 (Box 27, Folder 345)
        - "Chapter One," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Four," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Six," typescript photocopy, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript photocopy, undated
      - Manuscript, "My typed originals, incomplete.", undated
        - "Prologue," typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 346)
        - "Chapter One," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Sunday was the Lord's day..." typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Two," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "In the days of my childhood..." typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Three," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Five," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seven," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter (what? fill in please), Six," typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 27, Folder 347)
        - "Chapter number to come," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "The joy of hunting..." typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nine/Eight," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eight," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Nine," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Ten," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Eleven," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 27, Folder 348)
        - "Chapter Fourteen/Thirteen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Fourteen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Chapter Sixteen," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
        - "Prologue," typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 349)
        - "Chapter Seven/Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nine/Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Fourteen," typescript, undated
        - carbon
        - "Chapter Sixteen/Fifteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen/Sixteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter number to come," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Prologue," typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 350)
        - "Chapter Eight/Seven," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Nine/Eight," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Thirteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Fourteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Sixteen/Fifteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter Seventeen/Sixteen," typescript carbon, undated
        - "Chapter number to come, Eighteen," typescript carbon, undated
      - Manuscript, "First drafts--discarded pages--junk." Typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 351-352)
      - Manuscript "Excisions from original plus notes from publisher" and "aids and references.", undated (Box 27, Folder 353)
      - Typescript carbon and original with annotations, undated
    - American Trails Series
      In the mid-1950s Guthrie was asked by McGraw-Hill to be the supervising editor of a series of books on the "Great American Trails." These correspondence files document Guthrie's relations with the principal editors at McGraw-Hill and with the authors of the series volumes.
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill. Correspondents include: William Rainey, Thomas Clark, Savoie Lottinville, David Lavender, John Starr (McGraw-Hill), A.B. Guthrie Jr., Norman Fox, William Brandon, Felix Reisenberg, Samuel W. Taylor., 1956-59 (Box 27, Folder 354-355)
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill. Correspondents include: John Starr, Richard Dillon, Felix Reisenberg, George R. Stewart, A.B. Guthrie Jr., Walter Johnson, Edward Kuhn (McGraw- Hill)., 1960 (Box 27, Folder 356)
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill. Correspondents include: Edward Kuhn, David Lavender, John Starr, A.B. Guthrie Jr., Richard Dillon., 1961 (Box 27, Folder 357)
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill. Correspondents include: Edward Kuhn, A.B. Guthrie Jr., John Starr, Carl Carmer, David Lavender, William Brandon, R.N. De Armond, Charles Lang, A.L. Hart (McGraw-Hill)., 1962 (Box 28, Folder 358)
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill. Correspondents include: Frank Taylor (McGraw-Hill), Robert Gutwillig (McGraw-Hill), Harold W. McGraw, Jr. (McGraw-Hill), Edward Kuhn, A.L. Hart, John Hess (McGraw-Hill), Walter Clemons (McGraw-Hill), Robert Stewart (McGraw-Hill), Brigham Madsen, Richard Dillon, A.B. Guthrie Jr., Lou Ashworth (McGraw-Hill)., 1965-67 (Box 28, Folder 359)
      - Correspondence--McGraw-Hill, 1968-75 (Box 28, Folder 360)
      - Manuscript. "Introduction to Trail Series, 1961," typescript carbon; also includes worksheets, proposals, and McGraw-Hill publicity brochures (Box 28, Folder 361)
    - Arfive (1970)
      - Correspondence. Research material a. Brown spiral bound notebook of research notes by ABG, holograph. b. Brown spiral bound notebook of research notes by ABG, holograph, 1970-71 (Box 28, Folder 362)
      - Manuscript, typescript carbon, undated (Box 28, Folder 363-366)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 28, Folder 367-368)
    - Once Upon a Pond (1973)
      - Correspondence. Reviews, newspaper clippings, 1973-74 (Box 28, Folder 369)
    - The Last Valley (1975)
      - Research. Holograph ink, two notebook tablets; Loose research material, undated (Box 28, Folder 370)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 28, Folder 371)
    - Fair Land, Fair Land (1982)
      - National Endowment for the Arts proposal. Correspondence, information sheets, and career profile by A.B. Guthrie Jr., 1973 (Box 28, Folder 372)
      - Research, undated (Box 29, Folder 373-374)
      - Manuscript pages. "Waste basket pages," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 29, Folder 375-376)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 377)
    - Wild Pitch (1973)
      - Research and Reviews. Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 378)
    - The Genuine Article (1977)
      - Reviews. Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 379)
    - No Second Wind (1980)
      - Reviews. Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 380)
    - Playing Catch-Up (1985)
      - Reviews. Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 29, Folder 381)
    - Murder in the Cotswolds (1989)
      - Manuscript, "First Draft of Cotswolds." Typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 29, Folder 382-383)
      - Manuscript, White Copy, typescript original, undated (Box 29, Folder 384)
      - Manuscript, White Copy, typescript original, undated (Box 30, Folder 385)
      - Manuscript, "Second Draft Originals," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 30, Folder 386-389)
      - Manuscript, [Author's corrected set], typescript original and carbon composite with annotations, includes publisher's marks, undated (Box 30, Folder 390-393)
      - Manuscript, White Copy with yellow page inserts, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 30, Folder 394-395)
      - Manuscript, White Copy with yellow page inserts, typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 31, Folder 396)
      - Galley, "Author's Marked Set," typescript photocopy with annotations, 1988 Nov 11 (Box 31, Folder 397-398)
      - Galley, "Master Proof Set," typescript photocopy with annotations, 1988 Nov 11 (Box 31, Folder 399-400)
      - Reviews. Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 31, Folder 401)
    - Four Miles From Ear Mountain (1988)
      - Manuscript, n.d., typescript of poems used in the volume, typescript photocopy with annotations, undated (Box 31, Folder 402)
    - Big Sky, Fair Land (1988)
      - Big Sky, Fair Land: The Environmental Essays of A.B. Guthrie Jr., edited by David Peterson, 1988
      - Manuscript. "Introduction, written 1987," typescript original with annotations, with author's signature; Reviews. Newspaper clippings, 1987 May 21 (Box 31, Folder 403)
      - Manuscript, part 1. Typescript original, "Our Lordly Mountains" to "Here and Hereafter.", undated (Box 31, Folder 404-405)
      - Manuscript, part 2. Typescript original with annotations, "Requiem for Old Ephraim" to "Acknowledgements.", undated (Box 31, Folder 406-408)
    - A Field Guide to Writing Fiction (1991)
      - Manuscript. Typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 32, Folder 409)
      - Manuscript, "Must be Original," typescript original with annotations, undated. (Box 32, Folder 410-411)
      - Manuscript, revisions and correspondence. Typescript original with annotations, 1990 (Box 32, Folder 412-413)
      - Manuscript, "spine die duplicate copy," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 32, Folder 414-415)
  - Articles
    Manuscripts without dates are listed before those with them.
    - "Old Cars, Old Loves," typescript original with annotations. Published in Montana Magazine. Second copy, typescript carbon, undated (Box 32, Folder 416)
    - "On Marrying A Younger Woman," typescript original with annotations. Published in Prime Time, undated
    - "Montana Winter--and Things," typescript carbon with annotations. Published in Westways, undated
    - Untitled, text for More Images of the Great West by Marc Gaede, typescript original with annotations. Second copy same as above, undated
    - "On Living in the Boondocks," typescript original with annotations. Published in Westways, undated
    - "Posse on the Marsh," typescript original with annotations; second copy as original citation; typescript original with annotations, with letter from American West, undated (Box 32, Folder 417)
    - "Loco," typescript carbon, "final draft.", undated
    - "Sunday Feature HTK--Earth Week," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "1st Bank Corp. Article," typescript carbon and photocopy composite with annotations, undated
    - "Case of Bad Medicine," typescript original with annotations, undated
    - "Case of Bad Medicine," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
    - "Ebbie," reprint article from Southwest Review; typescript carbon, undated (Box 32, Folder 418)
    - "Roads Running West--Harper's Magazine, to Oregon and Elsewhere," typescript carbon with annotations; second copy same but without annotations, undated
    - Untitled, published in Modern Maturity, typescript original with annotations; second copy as above, undated
    - "Fourth at Getup," typescript original with annotations; second copy, typescript carbon, undated
    - "The Keeper of the Key," typescript carbon. Second copy, adaptation for radio by Elizabeth Adams, near print, undated
    - "Idaho," typescript carbon, undated (Box 32, Folder 419)
    - "Bargain," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
    - "The Town I Like--Versailles, Kentucky," typescript carbon. "Montana," typescript carbon with annotations, undated
    - "Mountain Medicine," correspondence, 1948-49 (Box 32, Folder 420)
    - "Kentucky," correspondence, 1951
    - "Adventure with History--Holiday Magazine, July 1953," typescript carbon, 1953 Jul
    - "Our Lordly Mountains--Holiday, July 1958," typescript carbons; correspondence, 1957-58 (Box 33, Folder 421)
    - "The Wreck," typescript carbon, 1959 Jul 21